<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Brief accompt of the Turks late expedition against the kingdome of Hungary, Transylvania, and the hereditary countries of the emperour together with an exact narrative of the remarquable occurences at the siege of Newhausel / translated out of the Dutch.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B18104</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10624223</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204706</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240878996</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4522B</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10624223</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B18104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1399:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Brief accompt of the Turks late expedition against the kingdome of Hungary, Transylvania, and the hereditary countries of the emperour together with an exact narrative of the remarquable occurences at the siege of Newhausel / translated out of the Dutch.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Hodgkinson and Thomas Mab,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed with privilege."</note>
                  <note>Incorrectly identified as Wing B4523.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Austro-Turkish War, 1661-1664.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Hungary --  History --  1526-1683.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Transylvania (Romania) --  History.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Nové Zámky (Czechoslovakia) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204706:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204706:1"/>
            <p>A Brief Accompt OF THE TURKS Late Expedition, Against the Kingdome of <hi>Hungary, Transylvania,</hi> and the Hereditary Countries of the EMPEROUR: Together with An Exact NARRATIVE of the Remarquable Occurrences at the Siege of NEWHAUSEL.</p>
            <p>Translated out of <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed with</hi> PRIVILEGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Hodgkinson,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Mab,</hi> MDCLXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:204706:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204706:2"/>
            <head>A Briefe Accompt OF THE TURKS Late Expedition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the Grounds of the Late <hi>Turkish</hi> Warre, which by Many Men, both Learned, &amp; Unlearned, has been long since
<note place="margin">(a) See the Writings of Dr. <hi>Philip Nicholas</hi> foretelling the incursion of the <hi>Turks</hi> into <hi>Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endome</hi> 7. years before 1670.</note> foretold, Severall Men are of Severall Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: Some Impute it to the Action of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotzi,</hi> in the Year 1657. in <hi>Poland,</hi> being under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken without the Consent of the <hi>Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior:</hi> Others, to other Causes; but the Most (with my Self) look upon it as the heavy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Heaven drawn down upon us by our multiply'd Transgressions; But it is not My Purpose to deduce the Causes of the Warre. I
<pb facs="tcp:204706:3"/>shall only acquaint the Reader with some Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marquable Passages concerning the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of This Barbarous Enemy against <hi>Hungary,</hi> and other Countryes Bordering upon him. To recite the Actions of Prince <hi>Ragotzi</hi> in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I reckon needless, as being already Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated in My <hi>Polonian Relations.</hi> And so God protect us from these Tyrannicall Proceedings.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1657. <hi>George Ragotzi,</hi> Prince of <hi>Transylvania,</hi> finish'd his Warre in <hi>Poland;</hi> and with much ado, made his Retreat to his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality; where he found, too late, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme Misery which he had brought upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. For so it was, that the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the worst Construction of all <hi>Ragotzi</hi>'s Actings in <hi>Poland</hi> (which Kingdome was then in Amity with the <hi>Turk</hi>) resolved to punish This Undertaking in his <hi>Vassall,</hi> as an Affront to the State of <hi>Turky.</hi> Upon the Apprehension of which Consequence, Prince <hi>Ragotzi</hi> put himself into a Posture of Defence, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of his Power. In 1658. he was yet at Quiet; but in 1659, the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> pour'd in a Numerous Army of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> into <hi>Transylvania;</hi> who practis'd all the Insolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Outrages of Burning, Killing, Ravish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (and the like) imaginable. This Horrid
<pb facs="tcp:204706:3"/>Invasion of the <hi>Infidels</hi> was valiantly oppos'd by <hi>Ragotzi</hi>'s Forces, Skirmishing with them at severall times very successefully, and so long as <hi>Hee</hi> liv'd, his Forts were not Attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Soon after; the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> no longer brooking this Audacity in his <hi>Vassall,</hi> dispatch'd an Embassadour to the <hi>Emperour</hi> at <hi>Vienna,</hi> with Rich Presents; desiring his <hi>Imperiall</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty not to concern himself in Prince <hi>Ragotzi</hi>'s Affaires, the <hi>Turkish</hi> Emperour being resolv'd to persecute the sayd <hi>Ragotzi</hi> to the highest De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Extremity.</p>
            <p>In 1660. the <hi>Turk</hi> lost no time; but sent a greater Force then before, into <hi>Transylvania.</hi> In the mean while, Prince <hi>Ragotzi</hi> march'd with a considerable Force before <hi>Hermanstad,</hi> and it came to a Bloudy Encounter, wherein <hi>Ragotzi</hi> deported himself valiantly, killing 17 men with his own hand; and so the <hi>Infidels</hi> for That Bout were forced to quit the Field, and leave the Victory to the <hi>Transylvanians,</hi> leaving like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise upon the Place, 6 or 7000 <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars. Ragotzi</hi> in the Persuit received 5 wounds, and 5 dayes after This Fight (<hi>June</hi> the 6th) he was brought to <hi>Great-Waradin,</hi> where he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this Life.</p>
            <p>The fall of this Prince ballanced the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Victory, and exceedingly Animated
<pb facs="tcp:204706:4"/>the <hi>Turks,</hi> who pressing more and more eagerly upon the <hi>Transylvanians,</hi> drove them every where to their strong Holds: Whereupon General <hi>Souche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had Order from <hi>Vienna,</hi> to draw toward <hi>Transylvania,</hi> and make it good against the <hi>Turks;</hi> and he forthwith march'd thither with a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Body, &amp; possess'd himself of several Holds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> the 14 of the same year, the <hi>Turk</hi> with 100000 Men laid close Sieger to <hi>Great-Waradin,</hi> which was stoutly defended by one <hi>Marcus Claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> a <hi>Scotchman,</hi> the Governour of the Town. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Siege, the <hi>Turk</hi> sent abroad strong Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes to subdue smaller Towns, forcing the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto several works, as the building of Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and the Like, putting them to the sword at last for their Reward: At one time killing 150 <hi>Christians,</hi> and at another, Loading 20 Wagons with <hi>Christians</hi> Heads which they carryed away.</p>
            <p>On the 6 of <hi>August,</hi> That brave Souldier and Governour <hi>Marcus Claudius</hi> was slain by a shot, and (the Besieged being left without any hope of Relief) This strong Place was surrendred unto the <hi>Turk</hi> upon Accord; being a passage into <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sylvania, Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Ragotzi,</hi> there started up One <hi>Barkay,</hi> a Creature of the <hi>Turks,</hi> making himselfe Prince of <hi>Transylvania,</hi> whom the <hi>Turk</hi> protected and supplyed with Forces, whereby he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204706:4"/>undertook to reduce several Places, siding in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with General <hi>Souches</hi> (who well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood this violence of the <hi>Turks,</hi> to be a designe not only upon <hi>Transylvania,</hi> but also upon the <hi>Empire</hi> it self,) and making Large promises un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hand, that whatsoever he got by the <hi>Turkish</hi> Ayd, was meant for the good of the <hi>Emperour,</hi> to whom he Intended a Just and an Honourable Restitution, reserving only <hi>Waradin</hi> to remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of the Prince of <hi>Transylvania;</hi> but the matter prov'd otherwise in the end.</p>
            <p>Toward the Close of this Year, a <hi>Blazing-starre</hi> appear'd with the Tayl toward <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and the <hi>Head</hi> toward <hi>Transylvania,</hi> which was but a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of the ensuing Calamityes.</p>
            <p>Soon after This, the <hi>Labolizish</hi> Peasants Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell'd against the <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>Transylvania,</hi> whom they partly put to the sword, some they took Prisoners, and others they sold to the <hi>Turk,</hi> The Right successour of <hi>Ragotzi</hi> was <hi>Kemini Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos</hi> (by many <hi>Transylvanians</hi> receiv'd and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn'd for such) who was bitterly persecuted by <hi>Barkay</hi> and the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1661 He fought them at <hi>Thassabat,</hi> and made a great slaughter: but at Last, oppressed with Numbers, he left <hi>Transylvania,</hi> and retrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Tockay.</hi> And now it appear'd that the <hi>Turks</hi> Business was not to stop there, but to fall also
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204706:5"/>upon <hi>Hungary.</hi> Whereupon his <hi>Jmperial</hi> Majesty granted Commissions for the raising of an Army, which was dispatch'd, part of it into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and part into <hi>Transylvania.</hi> In the <hi>Interim;</hi> Count <hi>Nichola Serini</hi> began to look to himself, and rais'd a strong Fort on the Wall over against <hi>Canischa,</hi> Naming it <hi>Serinswar:</hi> getting together a strong Body of <hi>Croats,</hi> and other Nations, that lay heavy upon the Quarters thereabout: which the <hi>Turks</hi> stomach'd not a little, however they carried it fair at present, &amp; for a while they talk'd of nothing but Peace, but at last they brake out into high expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, that they would have <hi>Serinswar</hi> demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish'd, Count <hi>Serini</hi> punish'd, and <hi>Transylvania</hi> subjected to the Power of the <hi>Turk</hi> by way of Reparation. None of which followed; but the <hi>Christians</hi> lookt upon it as every mans Interest to do his Best to defend himself a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Ambition, and Outrages of This Common Enemy; and there being nothing now to be expected but a great <hi>Turkish</hi> Warre, which was already begun by Parties; the <hi>Christians</hi> entred upon the Borders of <hi>Turky,</hi> drawing toward <hi>Stoel, Weissenburg,</hi> and <hi>Offen:</hi> and they subdued <hi>Zamock, Warda, Erzy,</hi> and <hi>Hirt:</hi> all these being inconsiderable Houses, and Castles, which with their Defenders were blown up, and fired.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:204706:5"/>
            <p>While this was doing, the <hi>Turks</hi> gathered together a Mighty Army Consisting of <hi>Asia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, African,</hi> and <hi>Europaean</hi> People; and from this <hi>Acheron</hi> issued those Devils in the shape of men, that have tormented <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> To this Numerous Army, they had likewise provided an incredible proportion of Victuals, Ammunition, and Artillery. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, several Treaties were set a foot, which the <hi>Turk</hi> so long insisted upon, till he had gained his End, and drawn a formidable Power into the Field, to break in upon the <hi>Christians,</hi> who laboured as much as in them lay, to preserve the Peace; but who can live longer at Peace then his Neighbour will give him leave? The Army of the <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>Hungary</hi> Consisted of 40000 <hi>German</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who had the <hi>Turks</hi> for their <hi>Open,</hi> and the <hi>Hungarians</hi> for their <hi>Private</hi> Enemies (The Animosity being so great, that many times it came to Blows betwixt the <hi>Germans</hi> and the <hi>Hungarians.</hi>) These Troups finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves under many Inconveniences, partly from the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who denyed Victuals to the <hi>German</hi> Army, and partly from diseases a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rising from the disagreement of the Climate, were much weakned, and diminished. <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> is questionless a very brave Country, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204706:6"/>abounds in Wine, and other Fruits; which taken to Excesse, breed dangerous Surfeits. The <hi>Hungarians</hi> in their deportment are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Grave, and Modest, but being Affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Germans,</hi> and others not of their own Religion, they are prone to revenge and hard to be Reconciled.</p>
            <p>Toward the Month of <hi>October,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Army was exceedingly pester'd with Surfeits, so that betwixt those that dyed; a Number that lay sick, and others that were carried out of the Country, it fell to a low Ebbe: and moreover; being then as far as <hi>Clausenburg,</hi> or thereabouts, they were put to some distress for Victuals and Forage: the Enemy encreasing daily more and more against them. (for in those Parts the <hi>Turkish</hi> Power was strongest) About this time, the Upstart Prince <hi>Barkay</hi> fell into disgrace, and the <hi>Turk</hi> preferred one <hi>Abasti</hi> to that dignity in his stead. Against <hi>Him, Kemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Janos</hi> bore up, Opposing him, and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters in the Head of 8000 men, and fortune so far befriended him in the first Engagement, as to deliver his great Enemy <hi>Barkay</hi> into his hands, whose Head he caused to be struck off, and then for a while the people flocked in to him, and Augmented his Army; But at last, he met with a Lions Fortune, when being sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204706:6"/>on all sides, and striving to clear his passage, he seemed onely carefull how he might fall with Honour: for his Army through many Skirmishes, Diseases, and great Scarcity of Provision, was melted away, and hope of Succour there was none left; the <hi>German</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by the like accidents being weakned and put to a Retreat. Upon these Terms it was, that he committed himself to places of more security, and in <hi>Sakmar,</hi> He with Others, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the Issue of the Treaty. But the <hi>Turks,</hi> (as has been said already) making use of a Treaty onely for their own Advantage, put themselves into a stronger Posture: In the mean time discharging their Choler with great indignation, one while against the Valiant <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> (that have held them tack so long in <hi>Candia</hi>) by and by against the divided <hi>Poloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and now and then against the half-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Transylvanians;</hi> but not a word all this while, nor so much as a look of displeasure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Fox-play</hi> of the Treaty lasted till the Year 1663, and then the Fury of these <hi>Infidels</hi> brake out, not onely upon <hi>Transylvania,</hi> and <hi>Hungaria;</hi> but upon the <hi>Emperours</hi> Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Countries also; yea, and upon the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> it self, This shall serve for an Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204706:7"/>to this <hi>Narrative.</hi> VVhat further oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd betwixt these two Parties, is expos'd and Publish'd at large, both at <hi>Francfort,</hi> and elswhere: so that I shall onely take notice of such Passages as happen'd since <hi>July</hi> 1663. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Turks</hi> Proceedings in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and upon the Borders, and what Opposition those <hi>Infidels</hi> have met with from the <hi>Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon <hi>July</hi> the 17. the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> came in great Pomp and Magnificence to <hi>Offen,</hi> encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping himself in the <hi>Pesterfield,</hi> being four <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> miles in Compass. His Army was upward of a hundred thousand men, above one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred great Guns, and of VVagons, and Beasts, a number not to be believ'd. His first work was to lay two <hi>Ship-bridges</hi> over the <hi>Danube;</hi> the one near to <hi>Gran,</hi> and the other not far from <hi>Parkam.</hi> His forces being quarter'd about those parts in Prodigious Multitudes, it was as yet doubtful, whether he would fall upon <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausel,</hi> or <hi>Raab;</hi> having his eye indifferently upon both, and lying still for a good while without action. But this Blood-Thirsty brute had shew'd himself much sooner, if a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall fall of Rain, and the Overflow of the <hi>Danube</hi> had not hindred him: However at length, he passed some Thousands of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my over the Bridge near <hi>Parkam</hi> toward the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204706:7"/>side of <hi>Newhausel;</hi> when immediately a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port was spread by some of the Pesants that were turn'd to the <hi>Turk,</hi> that the River had torn their <hi>Ship-Bridges,</hi> and that those 4000 <hi>Turks</hi> that had passed over, were now Cut off from the Main-Body. This Rumour it was, that inveigled the Governour of <hi>Newhausel</hi> (Count <hi>Forgats</hi>) into a Couragious, but an unhappy Resolution, which was, to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on those 4000 <hi>Turks,</hi> upon the supposition, that the Miscarriage of the Bridge had cut off their Retreat. It is very true, that he was ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly disswaded from that Attempt, and told, that the Body was greater then he imagined, but still persisting in his Resolve to fight them, upon the 28th of <hi>July,</hi> with his <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Hussars</hi> and <hi>Heyducks,</hi> and 11 Trcups of <hi>Germans</hi> and 500 Musquetiers (in all 6000 strong) he marched up to them and finding the Enemy foure times stronger then he expected, became sensible of the Abuse although alass! too late: for the <hi>Infidels</hi> having gotten certain Intelligence of the <hi>Christians</hi> design, and of their coming, caused the Bridges presently to be Repayred, which they had purposely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, and marching over with a strong Power surrounded them. The <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and <hi>Hussars,</hi> that were appointed to stand for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204706:8"/>a Reserve, seeing the Enemy come on so strong, betook themselves to flight; but the <hi>Germans,</hi> and <hi>Heyducks</hi> that gave the Onset behaved themselves stoutly, and sold a Dear Victory to the <hi>Turks.</hi> At last by Multitudes they were overcome, and those that could not get away, were miserably Cut, and Mangled. <hi>Forgats,</hi> and some few others escaped to <hi>Newhausel.</hi> This Combat lasted 3 hours, and about 3000 of the <hi>Germans,</hi> and <hi>Heyducks</hi> were put to the Sword.</p>
            <p>After this Victory, the <hi>Turks</hi> being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with encouraged, and the <hi>Christians</hi> not a little dejected, the Enemy made ready to lay a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Seige unto <hi>Newhausel,</hi> with what Success will be seen in this ensuing Information.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>An Exact Narrative of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marquable Occurrences at the Siege of <hi>Newhausel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ON the 15th of <hi>August,</hi> a Trouper of the <hi>Walterish</hi> Regiment, who in an Encounter had been taken Prisoner hard by <hi>Parkam,</hi> came to <hi>Newhausel,</hi> and Affirmed that the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> in his Presence, caused all the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204706:8"/>Prisoners to be put to the Sword, whereupon 40. of the Turkish Prisoners in <hi>Newhausel</hi> were Beheaded in Requital,</p>
            <p>On the 16th. <hi>dito,</hi> the Enemy marqu'd out the Forme of their Campe before <hi>Newhausel,</hi> openly.</p>
            <p>On the 17th. <hi>Newhausel</hi> play'd some Guns into the <hi>Turks</hi> Campe, that did Execution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Toward the Evening, the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> summon'd the Town, giving them three days to consider of a Surrender; but being An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered Negatively, the Enemy began to play upon the Fort.</p>
            <p>On the 18th. the <hi>Turk,</hi> with a great Shout, and a Peal of Cannon, Approach'd the <hi>Vienna-Gate,</hi> Posted themselves there, and present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell to digging, Notwithstanding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual shot made upon them; and over against <hi>Forgats</hi> Bulwork, they raised a Battery from Beneath.</p>
            <p>On the 19th. the <hi>Turks</hi> playd their great Guns, and continued till the 23th. making e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day at least 350. great Shot against the Wall, the Balle weighing 65, 48, 35, and 22. pound.</p>
            <p>On the 21th. the Besieged made a Sally, putting some of the <hi>Turks</hi> to the Sword, and took one Ensigne from them, whereupon the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204706:9"/>
               <hi>Turks</hi> in their Post at the <hi>Vienna-Gate,</hi> possess'd themselves of a <hi>Roundel,</hi> in which Action, many were slain on both sides.</p>
            <p>On the 25th. the <hi>Turks</hi> began to Batter the <hi>Vienna Gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 27th. there came one <hi>Turk</hi> into the Mote, who was taken Prisoner, and confess'd that he was sent to Scout, for which he was immediately knock'd on the Head.</p>
            <p>On the 29th. the <hi>Turkish</hi> Horse retired from the Fort, and drew near unto the <hi>Island Schutt,</hi> at which time they fired twelve Guns.</p>
            <p>On the 31th. the Enemy Attempted the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisado's,</hi> and began also to fill up the Mote; and on this day, Lievetenant Colonel <hi>Mortinisa Lamberg</hi> received a Shot, of which he dyed the day following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> the First, the Besieged, at night vowed to stand to it with their Officers to the last drop of their Bloud.</p>
            <p>On the 2d <hi>dito,</hi> a great Number of <hi>Janisa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> came into the Mote, against whom many shot were made, at which time it was suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed that the Enemy would give an Assault.</p>
            <p>On the 3d two Corporals were condemned to dye for deserting their Post.</p>
            <p>On the 5th 140 Auxiliaries came in from <hi>Comorra,</hi> and Lievetenant Colonel <hi>Hagen,</hi> was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204706:9"/>touched lightly with a ball of two pound weight, and upon the same day the <hi>Turks</hi> forced out of the Ground some of the Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sado's hard by the Fort, at which work, many of them were slain.</p>
            <p>On the 6th, the <hi>Turks</hi> Approached in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, to the Middle of the <hi>Town-Mote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 7th it rained, so that they could not work.</p>
            <p>On the 9th, Nine of the Defendents were killed by shott, and four of the <hi>Turks</hi> were slain by one <hi>Christian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 10th, an Officer was Condemned to dye for leaving his Post, and giving way to the Enemy.</p>
            <p>On the 11th, the <hi>Turks</hi> brake down the <hi>Vienna-Gate</hi> Bridge, which was repaired, and drawn up the next night; Many shot were this day made, and great Execution done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Enemy.</p>
            <p>On the 13th they played strongly with their great Guns, both upon the Wall, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City, but without much Harme.</p>
            <p>On the 15th the <hi>Turks</hi> made a shot just in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mouth of a great Gun in <hi>Newhausel,</hi> which made the Gun fly, and killed one man hard by it. In the Afternoon, 5 of the <hi>Turks</hi> that intended to passe the Mote, gave an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme, at which time the Lievetenant Colonel
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204706:10"/>of the <hi>Walterish</hi> Regiment was killed with a Shot.</p>
            <p>On the 17th the Marquis of <hi>Grana</hi> was hurt with a Bullet below the knee; but the Grand <hi>Captain</hi> was wounded in the Head, whereof he dyed; also between eleven and twelve of the Clock, the Enemy made an As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault in two places, which lasted till two, with great losse on both sides. At the Evening, the Besieged flung lighted <hi>Pitch-Barrels</hi> among the Enemy, which drove them out of <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick Sconce;</hi> but at the going out of the Lights, the <hi>Turks</hi> pressed in again with two foot Companyes.</p>
            <p>On the 18th. the <hi>Turks</hi> were working of a Mine, but the Besieged in their Counter-mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning drove them back; However by this means, they made a Breach in the wall suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a Passage; at which time, the Besieged stood but one pace from the Enemy, whom they forc'd to retreat with kindled Pitch-Barrells.</p>
            <p>On the 20th, the <hi>Turks</hi> climed over the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisado's</hi> and began to undermine <hi>Forgats-Sconce:</hi> and about foure in the after-noon they Attaqued <hi>Frederick-Sconce,</hi> and planted se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen of their Ensignes upon it; but were beaten off successfully, they likewise made an Assault upon <hi>Forgats-Sconce</hi> to their great losse.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:204706:10"/>
            <p>On the 21th they came on by night in great silence, and made another Assault; at which time an Eminent <hi>Bassa</hi> was slain, and two Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Besieged; and on both sides many Souldiers lost.</p>
            <p>On the 22th. they made another furious Assault, but they were repulsed with losse, and kept off with flinging of kindled <hi>Pitch-Barrels</hi> among them: yet they came on again, but to no purpose. At this Bout, the Besieged lost above 40. men, amongst whom were two Lieutenant Colonells, one whereof was a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> the other was <hi>Hagen:</hi> On this day, Marquis <hi>Pio</hi> was wounded in his head with an Arrow, and in his Neck he received another wound, Marquis <hi>de Grana</hi> was wounded also on the Head.</p>
            <p>On the 23th. the Enemy Battered so furiously, that <hi>Frederick</hi> and <hi>Serin-Sconces</hi> were beaten to the Ground, and a Breach made Large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for three Horse-men to have passed a Brest. This whole night they shot, without Intermission, and with Incredible Labour and delving, they raysed a Mount of Earth so high, that from thence, they could command the Town, and beat the Besieged from the Walls.</p>
            <p>VVhereupon the <hi>Hungarians</hi> whispered one another, to <hi>Surrender,</hi> (out of a fear to dispute it any longer) which moved the <hi>Germans</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204706:11"/>likewise to speak of an <hi>Accord,</hi> to <hi>Marquis Pio;</hi> who telling them that the Enemy kept no <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> one of the Souldiers replyed, that <hi>he did;</hi> and thereupon, the <hi>Marquis</hi> ran him through, and kill'd him: However, presently after, they sent to the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> demanding hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conditions, whose Answer was, that they should set down their own Terms, leaving on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their <hi>Great Guns</hi> in the <hi>Fort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 25th. the <hi>Turks</hi> were admitted to the <hi>Gran-Gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 26th. they stayd there till twelve at Noon, and then, the <hi>Christians</hi> marched out, with 2422 sound, and Armed men; many sick <hi>Germans,</hi> foure Piece of Ordnance with Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, for which the <hi>Turks</hi> allowed Horses, and VVagons, and Conducted the Garrison to <hi>Comorra.</hi> The <hi>Tartars,</hi> and some of the <hi>Turks</hi> fell to plundering of several Houses in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausel,</hi> and some of the VVagons of those that marched out; but a <hi>Bassa</hi> staid their hands, and kept them in order by force. At this Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Enemy got seventy piece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; great store of Armes, Powder, VVine, Meal, and Corn; Many of the <hi>Hungarians</hi> tarrying in <hi>Newbausel</hi> with the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>An Exact Narrative of the most Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marquable Occurrences at the Siege of</hi> New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausel.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:204706:11"/>
            <p>This Siege drew in many of the <hi>Tartars, Moldavians,</hi> and <hi>Wallachians,</hi> taking their March through <hi>Transyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania</hi> (where they began their Horrid Cruelty upon the <hi>Christians</hi>) toward the Camp before <hi>Newhausel.</hi> From Thence, <hi>September,</hi> the 3d. (being encreased to the Number of 20. or 30000. by the Addition of many <hi>Turks</hi>) they sought to make their way over the <hi>Waegh,</hi> which at last, they carried by force, putting those <hi>Christians</hi> to the Sword that Guarded the Passe, and so Crossing the Mountains, they Entred into <hi>Moravia,</hi> to <hi>Ʋngrishbrod, Hollishau,</hi> and the parts about <hi>Olmitz,</hi> which Towns, together with a great Number of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Villages, they burnt to the Ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many</hi> Christians <hi>they put to the Sword; Women, and Maids, these Bruits Ravished: The strong Men they tyed in Couples, and drove them along. Little Children they put into Sacks like</hi> Geese; <hi>some they cut in two, and others they dash'd against the Stones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Sun Blush, and the Rocks Weep at such Cruelty, and let the Earth open her Mouth and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up these Execrable Murderers! The Number of the Slain, and Captiv'd <hi>Christians,</hi> is reckoned to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ten thousand. These <hi>Barbarians,</hi> although Strangers to the Passes, and wayes of these Parts, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted yet no Guides: but furnish'd themselves with Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from among the <hi>Boores</hi> of the Country, whom they admitted likewise to their shares of the Booty: and in particular, they made use of the Treacherous Peasants of <hi>Werbouitz,</hi> little <hi>Werbte,</hi> and <hi>Rutzelau,</hi> to Conduct them over the Mountains: Whither the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple about <hi>Straswitz</hi> fled for Sanctuary; but were fetch'd from thence with 120. Wagons, and carried into Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity. The Count of <hi>Oppersdorff,</hi> Upper Governour of <hi>Brunner Crayses</hi> Escap'd narrowly to <hi>Brin,</hi> so sodain, and unexpected was this Invasion.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Septemb.</hi> 5th. The Enemy pass'd the River <hi>Mark,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:204706:12"/>and dispers'd themselves without Opposition; but the strong Towns they declined, being ill Arm'd, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fitted for a Pillage than a Combat. Upon This day they took the Prince of <hi>Dietrichstin</hi>'s Secretary, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his Lady, One Childe, and his Wives Sister, One <hi>Canonico,</hi> and others, as they were upon their slight from <hi>Nicolasburg</hi> to <hi>Bohaun.</hi> (Scituate among the Mountains) These being overtaken, the <hi>Canonico,</hi> with his Servant were put to the Sword; the Secretary made a strange Escape through a water; but the Lady, her Childe, and her Sister, they kept in their hands, with whom they danc'd at Night after their Barbarous rude manner at <hi>Popitz;</hi> till at last (according to the Report of Eye-witnesses) Sated with <hi>Lust,</hi> and <hi>Moravian Wine,</hi> they laid themselves to sleep; in such security, as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly signifi'd the Intelligence they had, that there were none neer to revenge the Fact. While they slept, the <hi>Sister</hi> made her escape; but the Lady her self, with quieting her Childe, waked the Dancers, who present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dash'd out the Childes Brains against the Wall. My Hand trembles at the writing of it! Oh! How many <hi>Christians</hi> are there that make this Horrid story their Sport, as if it were but a Fiction: as if the thing could not be done at all, because they were not at the doing of it. But I proceed,</p>
            <p>At <hi>Auspitz</hi> there came Gallopping six Troupers, habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after the <hi>German</hi> Fashion; and in broken Language, call'd for a Dinner in an Inn, and Provender for their Horses, telling the People they would pay for it. Being demanded, whence they came? They An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, that they were pursued upon the way; To which the <hi>Inn-keeper</hi> replyed, (as one well pleased with the Accompt) that if the Masters of the Town knew it, that were then met at the <hi>Councel-house,</hi> they would bid him welcome for his News. But before
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204706:12"/>the tydings could be carryed thither, there followed into the Town a great Body of <hi>Tartars</hi> after these scou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Troupers, who put Those that were then Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Councel, to the Sword, with many others; plunder'd the Town, and afterward burnt it to the Ground; but the Youths, and Children were most of them carried away for Slaves. Some of these Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Scouts were afterward brought Prisoners to <hi>Ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitz,</hi> and suffer'd Condigne Punishment.</p>
            <p>For Ten dayes This Havock lasted in <hi>Moravia,</hi> and then they pass'd over the <hi>Marck-stream</hi> into <hi>Austria</hi> (at which time, the Country People with their best move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vables were fled to <hi>Vienna.</hi>) At length, having laden themselves with all manner of Booty, they return'd to the Camp at <hi>Newhausel,</hi> where they exposed the Men, and Beasts, which they had taken up in several Places, to Common-sale in the Market: While these things were doing, the <hi>Turks</hi> busied themselves against the Fort <hi>Serinswar,</hi> and by way of <hi>Stratagers,</hi> attempted <hi>Clausenburg</hi> in <hi>Transylvania;</hi> but at both Places, they were repuls'd, with losse and shame. At which time Count <hi>Serini,</hi> with a Considerable Body of <hi>Croatians,</hi> and other Neighbouring People; made a sudden In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursion into <hi>Turky,</hi> to the great dammage of the <hi>Infidels.</hi> The Garrison of <hi>Comorra</hi> made diverse Sallyes upon the Enemies Camp before <hi>Newhausel,</hi> and spoil'd their Forage, which put the <hi>Turks</hi> upon a Necessity of fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it at a great distance: and no wonder if they did; for they had with them 26000 Camels; besides Horses, Buffles, Mules, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not to be numbred.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Spork</hi> made diverse Attempts in Parties, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Enemy; but most commonly they were too strong for him, which cost him many a brave Souldier. General <hi>Souches</hi> likewise, did all that was possible to way lay the Enemy, and defend the Passages: Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204706:13"/>Those that led into <hi>Moravia;</hi> but the <hi>Infidels</hi> marching alwayes in greater Numbers, then was repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, were too hard for him also.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hungarians</hi> were often desired to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into a Body against. This <hi>Common Enemy;</hi> but it seems they had no minde to it, till at last, after great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, Count <hi>Nicholas Serini</hi> undertook the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralship;</hi> and was by Prince <hi>Gonzaga</hi> presented <hi>General</hi> upon <hi>September</hi> 13. at the Head of the Army neer <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi> At which time, he drew together his <hi>Croats,</hi> and There joyning with the <hi>German</hi> Forces, under the Command of <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> they put themselves in a Posture against the <hi>Turks,</hi> but too late; for the Enemy before they were ready, was Master of <hi>Newhausel.</hi> Some <hi>Auxiliary</hi> Forces were drawn up also from the <hi>Empire,</hi> and took up their Quarters at <hi>Crembs,</hi> for Rest, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshment.</p>
            <p>While the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> was repairing <hi>Newhausel</hi> (where the Grosse of his Army continued for some time) the <hi>Tartars</hi> were order'd upon Excursions into <hi>Moravia,</hi> and forcing through the Passages at <hi>Selin</hi> and <hi>Rosingkau,</hi> they destroy'd the People thereabouts, and came to <hi>Wzettin,</hi> in the way to <hi>Silesia. Wzettin</hi> they burnt down, and <hi>Globau,</hi> and other Places adjacent; Partly Killing, and partly carrying People away into Captivity. Both Invasions were Barbarous and Bloudy; but having staid some few dayes there, they went their way. Their Aim was likewise to have broken through into <hi>Silesia,</hi> by the Passe <hi>Jablunca;</hi> but the <hi>Silesians</hi> kept themselves upon too good a Guard for that Bout, and have never been troubled with them since.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204706:13"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>